Finding Aid for Ruth Eckstein papers, 1962-1981
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ruth Eckstein papers 1962-1981 1962-1974
Eckstein, Ruth
0.4 linear feet
2014115 Aa 2
Ruth Eckstein served as a counselor at the University of Michigan from 1967-1981, and her research focused on minority and underprivileged students at the University and in the Ann Arbor area. The collection primarily contains information on the research topics that Eckstein pursued in the Ann Arbor area. The collection spans from 1962-1981 with the bulk of the material being from 1962-1974.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Bob Eckstein (Donor No. 10665 ) in November 2011.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Ruth Eckstein earned her B.A. in Sociology at the University of Wisconsin. She did her graduate work at the School of Social Service Administration at the University of Chicago. She then became a member of the American Association of Social Workers. Eckstein first worked as a family caseworker, but later shifted to vocational counseling. From 1967-1969 she served as a counselor at the Counseling Center at the University of Michigan. She then moved to the position of Academic Counselor for the Rackham Graduate School and the Office of the Vice President for Academic Affairs, from 1970-1971 and 1979-1980 respectively. Between these jobs, Eckstein served as a program analyst for the Opportunity Program through the Office of the Vice-President for Student Affairs from 1971-1981 and in 1975 she became a certified social worker. During this time, outside of the University, she worked as a vocational counselor in private practice and as a consultant for the Child and Family Service of Washtenaw County in Ann Arbor. In 1981, she left the University so she could expand her private practice and she became a consultant in vocational counseling to the Child and Family Service group of Washtenaw County.
Her early research involved studies of students recommended for counseling from the Ann Arbor area schools. As a social worker, she attempted to provide vocational, career, and academic counseling, including assisting people with job preparation and finding. While at the University, Eckstein worked on designing and developing research strategies for projects related to selected aspects of academic performance problems and progress of undergraduate students. Her counseling and research at this time was primarily focused on minority students.
She was married to Alexander Eckstein, the Chairman of the National Committee on United States-China Relations and professor of economics and specialist on China at the University of Michigan. They had one son, Robert Eckstein, who was born in 1951.
The Ruth Eckstein papers contain bibliographical information as well as correspondence to and from Eckstein. There is also information on the United Fund and Community Services organization which Eckstein worked with for a short time. The collection contains two series: Personal, Research, and Youth Programs in Ann Arbor.
Subjects:
Eckstein, Ruth.; Minorities--Education--Michigan.; Social service--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Coalition for the Use of Learning Skills.; University of Michigan. Opportunity Award Program.
- Personal
  The Personal series contains biographical information and some scattered correspondence.
  - Bibliographical Information (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1965, 1968, 1971-1974, 1981 (Box 1)
- Research
  The Research series contains files regarding Eckstein's research into black and minority student enrollment at the University of Michigan, and research on the effectiveness of the Coalition for the Use of Learning Skills (CULS) classes that the University offered. Various writings that she produced are also included, as well as student files from counseling cases she worked on and information on the Opportunity Program at the University where she did research and worked as a program analyst. The Vocational-Counseling Program was a research project that Eckstein worked on that offered counseling to students in need, as well as a project designed to analyze the current help that the students could receive from the school district.
  - Black Student Enrollment, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
  - Coalition for the Use of Learning Skills (CULS) Classes, 1974-1976, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Minority Student Enrollment, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
  - Opportunity Program, 1969-1974 (Box 1)
  - Writings (Box 1)
- Youth Programs in Ann Arbor, 1963-1965
  The Youth Programs of Ann Arbor series documents a project Eckstein assisted with that looked at what recreational opportunities were available for the youth in Ann Arbor and how these programs could be improved so that they appealed to a broader range of youth.
  - Final Report (Box 1)
  - Graphs (Box 1)
  - Notes (Box 1)
  - United Fund and Community Services, 1962-1964 (Box 1)